Nathanael Greene Papers 1777-1780 Mss.B.G83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1777-1780; 3 lin. feet
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 January 15; 3pp.; Greene, William (Box 2)
    Warwick - Acknowledging his favor by Col. Morgan. Moralizes on the appearance of luxury. Act enacted by General Assembly to force persons to sell articles possessed by them for the use of the army. Steps which should be taken by Congress to prevent further depreciation of money. William Littlefield's absence so prolonged that he has been left out in the pay abstract.
    viii, 37
  - to unknown correspondent, 1p.; Greene, William (Box 2)
    Number of men to be employed in the neighborhood of the navigable rivers in the Middle and Southern States. Duties of those employed in the Western expedition. Committee desires estimate of the cost of one year of such an army [fragment of letter].
    x, 59
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 January 29; 1p.; Hale, D. (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Enclosing the two letters which he apologizes for having shamefully neglected to deliver in Philadelphia. Will send yellow ochre and tin by a return express. Character of Col. Hay's stallion.
    i, 1
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 1; 4pp.; Hall, Benedict Edward (Box 2)
    Acknowledging Gen. Greene's (?) kindness in taking him to his suite. The kind of life he has led and is leading. Asks to be remembered to various people. Will attend him some time in April. Wants furlough for that time.
    viii, 39
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 January 27; 1p.; Hall, John (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - By direction of Col. Mitchell, forwards pair of canteens for Lord Stirling.
    viii, 71
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 February 1; 1p.; Hall, John (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - Asking that the enclosed letter be forwarded as speedily as possible, by a safe hand.
    ix, 78
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 February 2; 1p.; Hall, John (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - Asking him to see that the bearer, Mr. Alexander White, wagon-master, delivers a box of glass to Gen. Knox.
    i, 2
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1778 November 8; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - His Excellency requests that two sets of tools be provided and sent to Gen. McDougall to blow up the rocks, which greatly impede his carting.
    iv, 52
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 4; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - At the General's request, desires his opinion of the number of expresses necessary to be kept in constant pay.
    viii, 40
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 23; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - Desires to know by bearer how far the preparations for vessels have gone and the amount of material provided; the General's idea being to stop as short as possible, without leaving what is on hand incomplete.
    i, 4
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 20; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - Concerning Mr.Duryee's application to have his farm released, which was taken up for the use of the hospital. The General does not wish to discriminate, without sufficient reason, so refers the matter to Gen. Greene, in order that he may relieve Mr. Duryee, if it can be done without inconvenience to others or injury to the service.
    v, 40
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 22; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - By a letter received from Gen. Sullivan it appears that Poor's Brigade have left their tents behind. Asks that they may be supplied with them and other necessaries. Gen. Sullivan in "his usual pother, but dispatch is certainly very desirable."
    v, 59
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 May 31; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Middlebrook - Bidding him at the General's request to send some discreet person to ascertain the number of boats on the river.
    vi, 18
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 August 17; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - Desiring that he furnish a good horse, saddle and bridle to Lt. Whitehead, who carries important dispatches to Philadelphia for the General.
    iv, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 7; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - It is determined that Gen. Duportail and himself shall go to Count d'Estaing. Four horses will be necessary; therefore asks for an order on the person at New Windsor who provides horses for Gen. Greene.
    iii, 88
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 21; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Ordered by the General to ask if horses to carry the surgeon's chirurgical apparatus can be obtained from him [Greene] or from the brigades.
    i, 5
  - to Major Burnet, 1780 January 28; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    The General considers the application unusual, and does not think it proper to comply with it.
    i, 3
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 23; 1p.; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804 (Box 2)
    Headquarters - Orders from the General to send some pontoons (?) form Fishkill for the use of the officers.
    viii, 41
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 8; 1p.; Hand, Edward, 1744-1802 (Box 2)
    Mendham - The number of huts laid down in the general plan, viz., 24, to cover twelve men, not being sufficient, desires instructions immediately as to what alterations shall be made.
    i, 6
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 April 9; 1p.; Hansen, Peter (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Sends him at his request an account of clothing.
    xii, 26
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 11; 1p.; Harmar, Joseph (Box 2)
    Headquarters - Asking for an order for a saddle, as the duties of the inspectorship requires a great deal of riding.
    i, 7
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 6; 1p.; Harrison, Alex. Turner (Box 2)
    Desiring him to engage a hundred wagoners for one year, and telling him the terms he is to make.
    xii, 6
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 5; 1p.; Harrison, Robert Hanson, 1745-1790 (Box 2)
    Desiring to know whether the horses are ready for the officers going to Egg Harbor. If not, wishes them sent to New Windsor. Desires the express with the duplicate dispatches to be sent to Gen. Sullivan.
    iii, 89
  - to unknown correspondent, 1780 January 25; 1p.; Harrison, Robert Hanson, 1745-1790 (Box 2)
    Requesting him to transmit to His Excellency a return of the number of express employed in service.
    i, 9
  - to unknown correspondent, 1780 February 24; 1p.; Harrison, Robert Hanson, 1745-1790 (Box 2)
    Introducing the bearer, Daniel Halsey, an old soldier, who has a strong desire to become one of his expresses.
    i, 11
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 13; 1p.; Hart, William D. (Box 2)
    Paramus - Has sent out a party to secure a boat of his [Greene's], which drifted down. Difficulty of procuring anything on certificates, as the people are disgusted, no cash having been supplied to pay them since '77.
    i, 10
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 September 29; 1p.; Harvey, John, 1745-1812 (Box 2)
    West Point - Acknowledging favor of the 1st., recommending the appointment of Mr. Rice a deputy quartermaster-general to the convention troops. Believes Mr. Rice an honest man, but neither a good accountant nor well versed in the forms of business.
    iv, 30
  - to George Gray, n.d.; 1p.; Haws, Samuel (Box 2)
    Order to repair the bearer's bayonet.
    xii, 88
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 20; 1p.; Hay, Hawkes (Box 2)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging letter of 16th inst. Has written to Mr. Kearse to give him every assistance in removing his family and things out of the way of the enemy. Exceedingly sorry for his misfortune; offers any assistance in his power; has Gen. Washington's approbation for what he is doing.
    vi, 79
  - to Pynchon, George, 1778 May 21; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Concerning the building of three scows and one bateaux. Gen. Greene has ordered the matter put in execution immediately.
    xi, 89
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 January 3; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favor of 26th December, respecting artificers in Lt. Bolton's company. Will look into their complaints and, if just, they shall be redressed.
    viii, 57
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 5; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - So many complaints made to him and of him that he has requested the General for a court of inquiry. Desires hides sent on. Debt of the department to the artificers ought to be paid in money or clothes. Concerning his accounts. Will go to Congress on his own affairs as soon as Major Hale returns. Major Hale will handle the subject of cash with suitable eloquence.
    viii, 50
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 9; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Oversize 1)
    Fishkill - Smiths and wheelwrights determined to leave unless their wages are raised. By the offer of such extravagant wages, Mr. Simmons has a second time depreciated the money. He [Col. Hay] is even suspected of pocketing that part of the wages which, by leaving the post, the artificers can easily get elsewhere. Suggests procuring artificers from the regiment. Matter of cordage. Need of a proper public tanner. Pay for teams. Concerning the completion of the works at West Point during the coming summer. Hopes Gen. Greene is homeward bound, loaded with money. Enclosing two addresses, concerning the wages of workmen.
    viii, 42
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 9; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Asks that he will intercede with His Excellency to obtain clothing for the artificers, who deserve some encouragement for remaining at their posts.
    viii, 44
  - to George Clinton, 1779 January 20; 8pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Setting forth the difficulties of procuring teams for public service, and the unpleasant consequences of not getting a sufficient number of them. A most alarming circumstance is that the interest of the country and the interest of the army appear to be totally opposite to each other. Takes the liberty of laying before His Excellency certain hints which might, if the Legislature thought fit, aid matters. Pressing and immediate need of something being done.
    iv, 56
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 January 21; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favor of 14th inst. Sends the tin by Dr. Latimer. Cannot recommend his black horse which, like many of the fair sex, is slow and cannot bear fatigue.
    viii, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 21; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Oversize 1)
    Fishkill - Gentry of the staff have a considerable share in the alarming depreciation of the money. High price of teams. Waited on Governor Clinton with a letter to lay before the Assembly containing a plan for the quicker raising of carriages for public service. Delay in his accounts. Matter of returns.
    viii, 43
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 January 23; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Desiring to know the number and situation of tents the recipient of this letter has drawn.
    ix, 47
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 1; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favor of 26th inst. No problem of obtaining clothing for the artificers. Workmen's complaints concerning wages. Many evils which have arising from Col. Lewis' conduct. Sends return for December. Plan of putting tanyard near the banks of North river.
    ix, 45
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 10; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Oversize 1)
    Fishkill - Large supply of cash lately furnished, inadequate to pay the demands on the department; therefore entreats for another supply; thinks $ 100,000 will cover all debts. Desires his opinion on how fatigue men should be raised for the ensuing campaign; also the wages of certain workmen. Dispute with the justices as to the means of procuring teams. Legislature has brought in a bill nearly adopting his own plan for furnishing teams for the public service. The advantage of a uniform price in certain articles. Inconvenience of having no Justice of the Peace nearer than ten miles. Money needed to pay for wintering the horses.
    iv, 63
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 13; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - The bearer of this, Mr. Stewart, will wait on Gen. Greene for positive instructions respecting the wages of the artificers engaged by the day. Must not lose either the wheelwrights or the smiths. Has passed his word that the matter shall be fully settled by the end of the month.
    iv, 61
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 February 13; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Detailed orders concerning returns and accounts.
    ix, 48
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 18; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - In answer to his letter by Capt. Pendleton, has not heard a single complaint since the men joined Capt. Sizer's regiment. Were he convinced it would be of any service to the public, would willingly remove them.
    iv, 55
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 19; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Asking for a full supply of blankets. Difficulty in procuring teams. Oldest man in the country never remembers to have seen a winter so bad for the business of transportation.
    iv, 53
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 19; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Difficulty in procuring teams. Oldest man in the country never remembers to have seen a winter so bad for the business of transportation.
    iv, 54
  - to Sir James Jay, 1779 February 21; 4pp.; Hay, Udny (Oversize 1)
    Fishkill - Takes the liberty of making observations on the bill now under the consideration of the Legislature for regulating the impress of carriages for the army; makes certain suggestions and amendments. Thanks him and other gentleman of the Legislature for the indulgence he has met with on this subject.
    iv, 60
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 23; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging his favor of the 17th inst. Difficult to separate provisions sent to French fleet from provisions sent to American army. Received the $ 30,000, but would like the other $ 70,000 to fully settle his accounts. Little dispute with some of the Justices tolerably well settled. Enclosing his first letter to the Governor, proposing a new mode of raising teams. Will be glad of any amendments.
    iv, 58
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 24; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Concerning the method of paying Capt. Lamb's company of wheelwrights.
    ix, 46
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 11; 15pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Wagoners to be exempted from military duty during their term of service. Praises the Governor for the pains he has taken to serve the department. Difficulty of impressing teams. Wages of fatigue men. Question of forwarding the seven traveling forges. Scarcity of horses; the cheapest cost $ 1000 apiece. Waiting patiently for supply of cash. Col. Robert Livingston's iron works; needs 4000 cord of wood. Difficulty to procure pasture. Sends copies of returns. Payment of certificates for transporting baggage of the Convention troops. Asks for late resolve of Congress respecting treatment of staff officers charged with any crime. Wages of artificers. Has written Col. Smith to hasten the stores from Springfield. In want of canvas for tents. Gives reasons for differing with Gen. Greene about a court of inquiry.
    vii, 72
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 12; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - has just been informed of some clothing, which will be moth-eaten should it lie by all summer. Asks that a proper portion may be used for the artificers at the post.
    vii, 82
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 12; 4pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Praise for his assistants. Gen. Greene's recommendation to Congress to advance assistant quartermaster's pay to $ 140 per month at first sight appears generous; on second thought, considers it inadequate to their services, considering their expenses. Must raise artificers' wages or lose them. Officers of artificers beg dismission from the service, producing certificates to show that their families are starving for bread, - no wonder! with wheat at $ 25 per bushel!
    vii, 81
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 22; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Requesting a large supply of cash. Wages of artificers. His fears of a want of provisions for the army in the vicinity. The numerous calls upon the State of New York as compared with Connecticut. His differences with Capt. Starr on the subject. Has a severe tough of fever; if it continues, will be obliged to go to the seaside for a fortnight. Miscarriage of His Excellency's dispatches to Gen. Clinton.
    v, 54
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 26; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favor of the 24th inst. Will supply the Governor's wants as soon he knows them. Concerning the purchase of horses. Called up the night before by an express from Gen. McDougall, announcing probable attack by the enemy on his (Col. Hay's) quarters. His embarrassing situation without a penny to pay for anything. Will try to borrow from the Treasurer.
    v, 70
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 9; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Camp, Smith's Clove - His Excellency, Gen. Washington, desires return of all the boast on North river. Happy to hear of his success in the removal of stores. Questions of tents and canteens.
    vi, 35
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 14; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Smith's Tavern - Distressed for wagoners at Middle Brook. Begs that he will send him all the carters from his side of the river.
    vi, 69
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 19; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Directions of his Excellency concerning the places at which to deposit the public stores.
    vi, 76
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 20; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging letter of the 14th and 15th insts. has sent to His Excellency for permission to assist Col. Hawkes Hay in the removal of his family. Has written the Board of War for a copy of new regulations in the Barrack department, and to Congress for a copy of resolution respecting artificers.
    vi, 81
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 28; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    New Windsor - Enclosing letter to Governor Clinton. Forgot about it, owing to press of business. (copy)
    vi, 101
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 30; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favors of 28th, 29th, and 30th. If Col. Hay cannot go on with the business, he must make application for the aid of the line. Sorry he did not succeed with Governor Clinton. However, if all other sources fail, will furnish the horses himself, out of his own much needed number. Mr. Pettit expects to send him (Col. Hay) some money soon.
    vi, 99
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 30; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    New Windsor - In receipt of alarming accounts from the Board of War, they having been disappointed of a quantity of lead expected from Boston; if any has arrived at Fishkill or Claverack, wishes it forwarded to Newburg.
    vi, 103
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 July 8; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favor of the 8th, concerning the advisability of punishing wagoners. Thinks on the whole, although some little good might result from prompt punishment, yet the ensuing alarm would produce more injury than benefit to the department.
    x, 20
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 July 10; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    New Windsor - His Excellency's orders that the two Connecticut brigades shall be put in motion and marched down toward Norwalk. Concerning flour and portmanteaus for the brigades; also the teams to more their baggage with the greatest dispatch.
    x, 17
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 September 27; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    West Point - Acknowledging favor of 26th inst. Urging him to employ every person he can muster to aid in getting the boats ready. Will engage the artillery artificers to assist in the business.
    iv, 33
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 1; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favor of 30th ult., and will do his best to forward the boats. Must have fatigue men. Large quantity of forage at Claverack and other landings needs to be brought down. The bearer of this has fourteen horses to deliver, in tolerably good order.
    iii, 90
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 2; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Wishes copy of a certain resolve of Congress. The pay given the carpenters from Philadelphia, necessary as it was, has set all the rest of the department in a ferment. Comparisons being made all the time between New York and other States. Demands for higher wages. All this makes a very disagreeable situation. Difficult to get carpenters to repair bateaux.
    iii, 91
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 5; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Advises sending parties of twenty men each to Albany to collect all bateaux, etc., on either side of the river and bring them down to Fishkill Landing.
    iii, 92
  - to William M. Betts and other Assistant Quartermaster-Generals, 1779 October 6; 4pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging their favor and agreeing with them in the justice of their complaint. Begs them, however, not to desert their country at such a critical moment, but to remain until the close of the campaign, promising to do his best then to obtain some satisfaction for their grievances.
    iii, 55
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 7; 3pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Carpenters ready to work on the boats, but as yet no boards have arrived from Albany. Asks that a number of boards and planks be sent up from the fort and with them a small fatigue party to expedite the work. Uneasy about tar; expects to seize some, thought it be private property. Fourteen horses will set off for New Windsor.
    iii, 50
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 8; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Concerning a supply of tools for the carpenters. Totally destitute of handsaw files; advising him how to procure some more, and of the quickest way to send them.
    iii, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 9; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Enclosing extract from a letter of Col. Lewis. Thinks the building of the bateaux should claim precedence of the cooper's shop. Plenty of boards at Saratoga. Will forward any letter to Col. Lewis that Gen. Greene may think proper to write.
    iii, 52a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 10; 4pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favors of 7th and 9th inst. Disposition made of the 120 privates sent. Steps taken to purchase the needed boards. Duck enough to complete 170 tents, and will then patch up all the condemned ones. Thinks the vessels are sometimes unnecessarily detained at the fort; asks Gen. Greene to mention this to the engineer and Mr. Buchanan. Plans for getting sufficient hay. Question of the wages of bateaux men. Has sent to Col. Pettit for cash. Would it be possible to obtain $ 50,000?
    iii, 67
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 14; 2pp.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - Sends camp-stools by bearer. Will need large quantity of clothing. Wagoners destitute of blankets. Wants an answer from Gen. Greene to paragraph in Col. Lewis' letter relating to the raising of bateaux.
    viii, 53
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 14; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Fishkill - - Distemper raging among the horses has proved extremely mortal; the farrier, after a tolerably decent flogging, has run away; wishes a good one might be procured, who could save many of their lives. Camp-stools, which were forgotten, have been sent.
    iii, 68
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 15; 1p.; Hay, Udny (Box 3)
    Sends by bearer a chest with a lock of his own construction, which cannot easily be picked. Hopes it will please the General.
    iii, 69